<chapter>
    <title id="preface">Preface</title>
    <section>
        <title>About naming and references</title>
        <section>
            <title>Bean archive</title>
            <para>
                A bean archive is a java archive, such as a jar or a Java EE
                module, that contains a special marker file:
                <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code>.
                A bean archive may be deploy in a CDI environment. It enables
                all CDI functionality in that bean archive.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>OSGi bundle</title>
            <para>
                A bundle is a Java archive, such as a jar or a folder,
                that contains a special marker file: <code>META-INF/Manifest
                .MF</code>.
                A bundle may be deploy in an OSGi environment. It enables
                all OSGi functionality for that bundle.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Bean bundle</title>
            <para>
                A bean bundle is a java archive that contains both special
                marker file: <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code> and
                <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code>.
                A bean bundle may be deploy in an OSGi environment using
                Weld-OSGi infrastructure bundle. It enables both OSGi and CDI
                functionality for that bundle. It also enables Weld-OSGi
                special functionality.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>References</title>
            <para>
                This document uses both CDI and OSGi specification
                documentations as technical references. You may refer to these
                documents for a better understanding of CDI and OSGi
                functionality, references and naming conventions.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is Weld-OSGi ?</title>
        <para>
            Weld-OSGi aims at simplifying the access to the OSGi environment
            by providing a more modern, more user-friendly and faster way to
            interact with the OSGi Framework.
            It addresses the OSGi complexity about services management using CDI
            specification (JSR-299). Thus it provides an CDI-OSGi extension
            with injection utilities for the OSGi environment.
            Moreover an integration with any CDI implementation, such as Weld,
            is possible through a standard bootstrapping API. An complete
            integration with Weld is provided.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What about other frameworks</title>
        <para>
            Weld-OSGi stays compliant with CDI specification and uses only
            standard OSGi mechanisms. Every things it does (or nothing from
            it) CDI and OGSi can do.
            Thereby is compatible with most of the current frameworks dealing
            with OSGi service management.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
